Previously on Gotham...
You're the brother I never had.
We will create a legacy in this city.
Gotham falls, we rise.
Together.
Poor Jim.
All alone again.
I told you to leave.
I heard you.
So many things I wish I could change.
Things I have done.
We're here now.
We'll try to put the pieces
back together again.
Jim, I'm pregnant.
This isn't you.
We're not the same.
That night that your parents
were murdered,
I didn't do anything
because I didn't care.
Everyone, let's dig a little deeper.
Because that's the only way
you're all making it out of this hole.
Deep enough?
You're leaving Gotham.
There's nothing left for me here anymore.
I've done all I can.
I want in.
I love family reunions.
Don't you?
Go. Go, go.
- Which way?
- Wait.
General, you were the ones who let Walker
operate right under your noses.
Now you're telling me she evaded capture?
I understand your frustration.
Have you at least determined
why she did what she did?
Not yet.
Look, bottom line, Walker and Dorrance
are out of the picture.
What else is standing in the way
of reunification?
Nothing.
I'm recommending we begin the process
immediately.
There have been a lot of promises
from across the river.
But unlike Walker or whoever she is,
I have the authority to take action.
Unless something happens
to destabilise Gotham again,
this nightmare is about to end.
Think he's for real?
I'll believe it when it happens.
I take it your search party
didn't find Alfred.
Neither hide nor hair.
Pennyworth vanished five days ago.
It ain't looking good.
How's Bruce?
He's been pulling double shifts
on the search parties.
Kid's dead on his feet.
I wanna search this area next.
There are whole blocks
of abandoned buildings.
I'll get a squad right on it.
Just give me five minutes. I'll be ready.
You're not going out.
- No, Jim--
- You need your rest.
I'm not cutting you out,
but I need you sharp, not a liability.
I just don't understand
what could have happened.
Neither do I.
But I know that Alfred Pennyworth
can take care of himself.
I'll send for you if I hear anything.
- Kid's tough.
- Yeah.
In other good-ish news, Harper radioed.
Her squad found something.
What?
It's weird.
Four men.
Looks like they breathed in some
sort of chemical agent.
I'm thinking airborne.
And the Z's on their bodies?
Carved into them before time of death.
Check out the moustache.
Fake.
Seems like they escaped from here.
A film set?
I said it was weird.
Z's on their chests.
Think it could be Zsasz?
Chemicals aren't really his MO.
Plus, I never figured Zsasz
for much of a cinephile.
But whoever it is,
if they have more of these chemicals
and the will to use them--
It's bye-bye, reunification.
Gotta stop him before news
reaches the mainland.
The Chessmen.
That's a gang that operates
out of the Narrows.
What the hell is a Narrows gang
doing way up here?
I think we both know someone we can ask.
Can you check on the fever in Bed 12?
What's up, Doc?
Heard you were working here.
Interesting.
It's what I do, help people.
Speaking of which, I've got patients.
Oh, you wouldn't kick Jim's baby mama
to the kerb now, would you?
Whatever happened between you and Jim,
it's none of my concern.
- So if you're here to gloat--
- I'm here for medical assistance.
For my little nugget.
What do you say? Be my OB?
- You can't be serious.
- I know we've had our differences.
You tried to kill me, Barbara.
Twice.
That was years ago.
There are other doctors here.
Not as good as you.
Look, whatever you think of me,
my child is innocent
and I want the best for it.
And in this place, that means you.
- Does Jim know you're here?
- This is none of his business.
Lee?
Jim.
- Barbara.
- You're interrupting.
Doctor-patient. Blow.
- I'm sorry, you're her doctor?
- No.
I don't know. Maybe.
What are you doing here?
Some bodies turned up.
They might have a Narrows connection.
I wouldn't have come but--
It's important. Right.
You two need to talk.
- I'll be outside.
- I'd rather not.
If you want me to be your doctor,
you will talk to the baby's...
father.
Your first appointment is next week.
The nurse will give you all your vitamins
when you leave.
Deal?
Is she really the only one you could find?
She's the best doctor
in this hellhole of a city.
Not everything is about Jim Gordon.
Pretty sure this one is.
Because we slept together. Yeah.
I only told you because I felt
you had a right to know,
but your involvement in this ended
the moment you put your pants back on.
What?
- You don't think I'm fit to be a mother?
- What do you think?
Barbara.
Who are you?
Well, look who decided to join us.
Hello, champ.
Master Bruce!
Alfred, how did you...
Look at the state of you.
What have I told you
about rolling around in the muck?
Alfred.
What's going on?
Who are these people?
Whatever do you mean, Bruce?
We're your parents.
Right. Well, let's get you spruced up.
After all, we have a guest.
Welcome home, Bruce.
Jeremiah.
You're alive.
Well, you didn't think Selina
could kill me so easily, did you?
I just had to put you off my scent
until I could finalise my project.
Manners, Master Bruce.
Let's not be rude to our guest.
Especially when I come bearing gifts.
Oh, Mr. Jeremiah. A cake.
How exceedingly kind of you.
Is it Italian meringue?
- Sure.
- Oh.
Now, now, Bruce.
You come any closer and I blow up
Wayne Manor with all of us inside of it.
I have a dozen more of these
Italian meringues
sprinkled all throughout the house.
What did you do to Alfred?
And who are these people?
Glad you asked. Come.
Come, come.
Mummy and Daddy dearest
were just an innocent couple I kidnapped
based on bone structure and...
build.
Just a touch of plastic surgery
and voila...
Waynes.
Alfred, I nabbed in the Green Zone.
They're hypnotised.
Well, I'm afraid there was no room
for improv in our script.
Today is a very important day, Bruce.
Just look at the way they're dressed.
It's the night my parents were killed.
And I'm giving you the chance
to experience it all over again.
- Why?
- Isn't it obvious?
Bruce...
this, this was the most important day
of your life.
And I didn't get to be a part of it.
We need to rectify that.
Alfred.
It's time for dinner.
Chop-chop. We're on a very tight schedule.
Of course, Mr. Jeremiah.
That's zero for three.
Yes.
It seems the government was quite thorough
when they mined the river.
You didn't have a plan
to get off this rock
before you stole everyone's crap?
I was working on a plan.
The river is mined.
Everything that flies out
gets blown from the sky.
What?
Jeremiah was digging a tunnel
under the river.
A tunnel?
Really?
Do you have any better ideas?
Didn't think so.
It's in the Dark Zone.
We should wait until night
to check it out.
Well, I was running out
of guinea pigs anyway.
Oh, look.
He's swimming to shore.
Are you sure you should be out
in the Narrows alone?
When the bridges fell,
this place descended into chaos.
Figure our best bet of getting out
in one piece
is to keep a low profile.
So all the work I did
to make the Narrows better
was for nothing.
It's the Leopards,
Rivals of the Chessmen.
It's pretty bad.
- About this Barbara thing...
- Jim, just don't.
No, it's important to me
that you understand.
Okay. So, what are you gonna do?
I don't know but it's my child too.
Barbara seems
to have a difference of opinion.
But, hey, people change.
You don't know her like I do.
You can say that again.
Look.
We're clear.
The Chessmen moved around.
They used these
as signals for their members.
The rook's a compass needle.
North-northeast. Let's go.
Alfred told me such great tidbits
about your childhood.
How you used to eat here in the kitchen
when it was just you and the family.
My, how homey and intimate.
Grilled cheese
and Branston pickle sandwich,
Mr. Jeremiah.
Master Bruce's favourite.
My influence, though, Thomas did add
a dash of aioli for extra flair.
Oh, Come on, Bruce.
That's a weird favourite food
for a 12-year-old.
I'm playing your game.
Now let Alfred and these people go.
They're innocent.
I'm sorry, Bruce, it's just.
It's very important to me
that I get every detail exactly right.
Speaking of which, the final touch.
What was it like...
losing your parents that night?
I lost my family too, Bruce.
The wound still hasn't healed.
I think about it often.
None of this is real.
You're trying to manipulate me.
It will never be real.
But you are thinking about that night.
And that's all I need.
I just want to be connected to you.
I offered for you to be my best friend!
But I've realised
if we can't be friends...
then we can be connected in other ways.
How?
You'll see.
In time.
I'm sorry to cut tonight short.
But...
your parents and I
have a very important date...
- Jeremiah.
- with destiny.
Jeremiah!
You might want
to find your faithful butler and leave.
Quickly.
Alfred!
The signs lead this way.
Look at the smoke.
Someone restarted production.
My God, Jim.
Look at all of this.
Come on.
- Who's in charge here?
- Tick tock.
The chemical stock,
shall give our Gotham an aftershock.
Tick tock, the chemical stock,
- Tick tock...
the chemical stock,
shall give our Gotham an aftershock.
They've been hypnotised.
Tetch.
Tick tock, the chemical stock,
shall give our Gotham an aftershock.
My, my, what a thrill.
Jim Gordon...
and the woman he told me to kill.
Brings back memories.
That tea party, so long ago.
But now to order these men
to attack my foe.
All for one and one for all!
Ain't this a grand old ball!
- Jim!
- Ain't this some game!
Give it to me again?
Penguin has been stealing everything
in the city that's not nailed down.
And now he needs
a way of getting it off the island.
And you're helping him?
Well, that's what he thinks.
Barbara, Tabitha was my friend too.
If anything, I want to gut the twerp...
and take his loot.
Except you don't actually have a way out
of Gotham.
I'll find one tonight.
I'll still need your help
moving the stuff.
We can get out of here together.
Away from Jim Gordon.
Rich as Midas.
Penguin dead in a ditch.
Well, aren't we just two single ladies
and a baby
about to kill our sworn enemy together.
What?
It's just you're pregnant.
Don't even start.
Alfred!
Alfred.
- We need to get out of here.
- Ah, Master Bruce.
I was just taking a quiet moment
to tidy up.
We need to go. The bombs.
- What bombs?
- These bombs.
No need for roughhousing, sir.
There has to be a way.
Alfred,
you'd do anything to protect me, right?
Absolutely, sir.
There's a gas leak. In the kitchen.
It's only a matter of time
before this whole place goes up.
A gas leak?
Where are your parents?
Where's our guest?
I've already warned them.
I know a way out. Come on!
Alfred!
Alfred.
- Oh, bloody hell.
- Don't move.
Do you...
Oh, yeah, I remember everything.
Clear as day.
Let me tell you, if ever I see
that Jervis Tetch character again,
I'll stick that watch so far up his...
his nose.
How about you?
You all right?
Yeah, I'm all right.
The manor...
Don't you worry about that now, son.
Come on. Help me up.
Oh, your leg's hurt.
Yes, but it's not broken.
I thought I lost you.
Me?
Never, Master Bruce.
Go on.
You know where he's gonna be at.
Go.
If you're here,
Jeremiah must still be alive.
And if you're here,
I'm guessing you found our test subjects,
all boiled and bubbled.
What's he planning?
It's a surprise, don't you know?
A real killer.
Shall I hypnotise our friends here
and have them slit each other's necks?
Nix.
Better check with the boss.
He might have other ideas.
I'm sorry I got you involved in this.
Don't be. I knew
what I was getting myself into.
- I know, but, Lee...
- Jim,
whatever you want to tell me,
save it till we're out of here.
Fair enough.
We need to find
out what Valeska's planning.
Hey, Tetch.
You know, it's funny.
I never figured you
for Jeremiah's errand boy.
Oh, Captain.
No errands do I run.
This is simply a way for me
to have some fun.
Tell yourself that.
What are you when you would take away
your games and your rhymes?
Nothing but a second-rater
with a really silly hat.
Shut up.
Beautiful. Beautiful.
Lee Thompkins, you do intrigue me so.
First, you were a doctor,
then the Narrows Queen.
Tell me, please do,
are you running from your past
when you become someone new?
When I found Jeremiah,
he had a bunch of crazies
digging this tunnel for him.
Well, that certainly fills me
with confidence.
You hear that?
- Alfred.
- Selina.
What are you doing here?
And with that?
I should ask you the same thing.
What's down that tunnel?
Well, it was Wayne Manor
till Jeremiah blew it up.
He sealed the only way out of Gotham.
No. Jeremiah is not alive.
I saw him die right here.
Yeah, well, you're wrong.
We all were.
And now, he's embarked
on some madcap scheme
where he's re-enacting the night
Bruce's parents were killed.
- Where's Bruce?
- He's gone after Jeremiah.
He could use your help.
Wait.
You think that because
I did not kill Jeremiah
does not mean that I won't kill you.
- Selina.
- You killed my friend Tabitha.
- You deserve to die.
- Selina.
Just put the knife down.
Bruce needs you.
I suppose I should thank you.
Or you could help me to the Green Zone.
Of course. It's that way.
Jeremiah!
Show yourself!
Ole!
Hola, Bruce.
Well, here we are,
the theatre where your Mummy and Daddy
took you to see The Mark of Zorro.
I had heard you were obsessed
with this man as a child.
I wonder what was
it that intrigued you so?
Was it the fact that he struck fear
into the hearts of his enemy?
En garde!
Take that, you villain.
Vagabond.
Scoundrel.
Warned you.
Perhaps the movie was a bit too effective.
Isn't this the part
where you became frightened?
When you asked your parents to leave?
I wonder what would have happened
if you hadn't done that.
If you had conquered your fear.
Maybe your parents would still be alive.
Well, on to the last and final stop
down memory lane.
Stop!
- That's far enough, Bruce.
- Jeremiah.
- You don't have to do this.
- But I...
I do.
You see, I came to this realisation.
I realised that no matter what I did
to bond us,
some random gunman in an alley
would be the man
who you were tied to the most.
The man you saw when you close your eyes.
I want to be the star of the show.
So if I can't have you as a brother
bonded by love...
then we'll just have to be bonded
by hatred.
And you think killing two people
that look like my parents will do that?
It won't.
Well, then it's a good thing
I already put a bullet
in both of their fraudulent skulls.
Oh, you're confused.
You're wondering if I already shot them,
then who's this lovely couple?
Thomas, Martha...
why don't you turn around?
Jim!
I know.
See, over the course
of our little adventure,
fate brought to me James Gordon
and Leslie Thompkins,
and I thought to myself...
why not...
why not kill the man who you think of
as your second father figure?
And your dear, dear,
dear friend Lee Thompkins.
And when I do,
finally, you and I will be bound together.
Because you see...
re-unification with the mainland
hangs on by a thread.
Those fireworks go off
and toxic chemicals rain down
onto the city,
and the government...
cuts us adrift for good.
Jeremiah.
Don't.
The piece de resistance.
One last thing.
I had Jervis Tetch hypnotise them,
so that they'll wake up the moment
these beautiful pearls hit the ground.
I want you to see them realise
what I've done to them
as the life drains from their bodies.
Never forget, this is all for you, Bruce.
No!
Selina, the pearls!
Ecco!
Now!
We need to stop the fireworks.
They're gonna...
I know. You go after Jeremiah and Ecco.
I'll take the truck.
There's no way to stop them all.
Get to Harvey.
Warn the people in the Green Zone
to get to cover.
What are you...
Jim!
Jeremiah!
Face me!
Here, Bruce.
Jeremiah!
This ends.
Tonight.
No.
No, Bruce. Now it begins.
Yes. You feel it.
The connection between us.
You do.
Don't you? Bruce, you feel it.
Tell me you feel it.
You mean nothing to me.
Why don't you understand?
You need me.
I'm the answer to your life's question.
Without me, you're just a joke...
without a punch line.
After all this time,
you've come to me for help.
After allowing Strange to put a chip
into my brain.
Attempting to sell me out to Gordon.
And after naming...
a dog after me.
First of all, I am very fond of that dog.
Secondly, I had Hugo Strange
save your life.
Thirdly, do you really think
I didn't have plans to save you
from Jim Gordon?
You always have an answer for everything,
don't you, Oswald?
We have been through all of this before.
I've tried to kill you.
You've tried to kill me.
But here we are in this room. Together.
It means fate has different plans for us.
What are these plans?
Haven't you realised what Gotham is yet?
It is no longer a city.
It is a prison.
And I think it's time we escaped.
You heard the news?
Everybody's talking about it.
Reunification isn't happening.
Word of the chemical spill
reached the mainland.
No action until the government
can determine if Gotham is safe.
I figure at least a couple of months.
You don't sound surprised.
Guess, I'm not.
Could've been much worse.
You stopped that.
Every time I think
we're turning things around, I look up,
right back where we started.
What were you about to say to me
when Tetch had us?
I don't know.
I guess I...
would have said...
what I said the last time
we saw each other.
I wish I could go back.
Do things differently.
Better.
It feels like a long time ago.
Nothing's changed.
But it has, Jim.
- That was a mistake.
- A mistake?
Put yourself in my shoes.
After everything you said,
suddenly you're having a baby
with Barbara, of all people.
But it's not just that.
You talk about doing things differently
and I keep thinking...
what if we hadn't lost ours?
What are you doing here, Lee?
I don't know.
I know you've taken on so much, and...
and I want to be understanding, but...
you let me down, Jim.
I'm sorry.
What does that mean?
For us?
I don't know.
Can't change the past,
so I guess we just have to live with it.
No, Lee...
I can't believe he's still alive.
They've been doing scans,
and he has no brain activity.
He's no longer a threat.
To either of us.
Thank you for coming to help me.
That night your parents were killed,
I should have done something.
Selina, you've done enough.
It's not much, but it's home.
I've been looking
through your treasure trove.
You've been a very naughty boy.
Barbara?
How did you...
Selina?
She and I were gonna go murder-halfsies
to get you back for Tabitha,
but it seems I will have to do the dirty
work myself, as usual.
Oh, my God.
You're pregnant.
How could you possibly know that?
Look at you.
She's glowing.
You're glowing.
How very observant of you.
Adieu, Oswald.
Wait.
Come with us.
- What?
- Yes.
I killed Tabitha.
You're angry.
You want revenge.
But do you really want to raise your child
in a toxic waste war zone?
Come with us.
Are you telling me you found a way out
of Gotham?
Ed did.
- It's a submarine.
- A submarine?
It can track mines
in the river using sonar.
So where's this submarine?
We have to build it.
Yeah, I'm gonna shoot you.
God.
What is happening to me?
- Perhaps...
- Shut up!
That was a rhetorical question.
Fine.
I won't shoot you
for the sake of my child.
But I will never forgive you.
Of course.
I understand.
Call me when it's done.
- So who's the lucky father?
- Shut up!